okay we are now recording my friend
yeah so as i'm mindful actually right
now uh
what i would say is maybe a hope but
certainly a curiosity
and we both came into this with um
apparently some energy um
and i'm wondering if it's coordinated it
may not be they may actually just be
like completely different
i will uh to the degree to which what
you're bringing
a true degree which there's not a
natural harmony i will i will orient my
attention to what you're bringing
um so the thing that i came in with i
was just on a
call with zack stein and brilliant
one of the places that we that we found
ourselves in
and this is you and and greg and
actually even jordan peterson came to my
mind here which has to do with the
how do i say it right so the mental
health crisis
right it's part of the meaning crisis we
have the mental health crisis but the
mental health crisis is now going
hyperbolic yes
because the you know the context is
breaking us in many many different ways
yep um and i would even i would even say
just i would assert that from my point
of view
the the moves like the place we were at
is intolerable and there's really only
two moves one move is to sort of
find a way up the other move is to go
down yeah we're at a bifurcation point i
think
we're at a bifurcation point precisely
okay so
practically speaking one of the primary
challenges is the challenge of
how do we actually provision a
a capacity for supporting
individual mental health in the upward
direction
that is adequate scalably i.e scale
would be adequate to the magnitude of
the challenge
so certainly if we were to do something
like let's enroll
every professional mental health
practitioner
socialize that and make that available
into some triage mechanism
first of all that's insane there's no
way that would ever happen but even if
it did
it's orders of magnitude below the level
of capacity
in fine grained capacity that's needed
uh
because the mental health crisis has a
the downward movement has a reciprocal
closing dynamics we've got a we've got a
network effect moving working against us
so we need a network in fact
working for us yep i agree so one of the
uh i was kind of doing the hollywood
pitch thing where it's like throwing out
combos and
triads is almost like design constraints
like it's like
you know the player meets uh
the matrix so the dynamic was something
like gen z itself so targeting gen z
as a hey guys good news and bad news bad
news is
nobody's coming to help good news is
you may be able to bootstrap yourselves
with a little bit of help
with the amount of help that is coming
we may be able to work this out
right right and the triad was something
like
ender's game uh
book damon and
pardon by herman hessa the book no no
by daniel suarez it's like a science
fiction techno thriller okay
um and then something like what what you
know what you're working on with the
logos what what zach's working on with
the academy
which is to say a highly
peer-to-peer protocol a fundamental
protocol
where individuals can begin to get into
relationships that are generative i.e
in in operating the protocol the
interaction between individuals
within pretty wide latitudes will
serve to upgradient them as individuals
and their capacity to enter into
relationship with each other and with
others
so it's a a an auto
auto empowering network
empowering protocol right so
you're trying to create a virtuous cycle
to
counteract a potentially vicious cycle
yes and
so so for example i'll give some some
articles artifacts to the protocol
and i think this this first piece is
crucial i'll use the metaphor
of a of a of an electrical circuit
system
because i've been working on diy solar
power systems
um one of the things that shows up often
i think
and i'll use jordan peterson as an
archetype but there's many others in gen
z i think it's happening all over the
place
is individuals end up trying to hold
more of their social graphs total
need than is in fact right
which is to say more than they can so
they burn they burn out
and it's like if you think about it in
terms of building a a network
and then you build a circuit graph on
top of a circuit like an electrical
circuit on top of that
um you have to have the right amount of
the wire gauge
and the right kind of circuit breakers
for the amperage that needs to flow
through the
circuit right and and any particular
location that it shorts i
it's not grounded which i love the the
entendre of that will tend to have all
the current flow through it and it will
blow up
and so the key message here is as a
primary protocol as an individual
you have to take deep responsibility for
neither being
more nor less than what you need to be
in the context of your network
and if you're holding and this is jordan
peterson like he did the daedalus thing
or he did the
uh uh his his hubris was in fact to
endeavor to hold
more than was actually his to hold right
he was trying to
bear more people's crosses than his own
cross solo
and therefore this may or may not be
true but it's irrelevant as a metaphor
it's useful
and therefore actually more energy more
came to him than he could possibly
handle he actually became a lightning
rod
and the ambient energy that couldn't
flow where it needed to flow
found him went through him and just blew
him out as a circuit
and anybody who goes in that direction
or anybody who tries to do too much
will get blown out which ends up then
being a massive category here because
now you're no longer able to provide
to your network what you're supposed to
provide so not only you're no longer
providing more you're actually actually
actually providing less which creates
cascade failures
so as a protocol the protocol is to be
very careful
to recognize that you you are not
permitted you are straight up are not
permitted
to carry more than is in fact yours to
carry
and a primary virtue is to have very
fine-grained nuance like
deep sensitivity to that and noticing
that it's crucial for you to
pull away from things when that energy
is flowing
towards you when you're reaching your
limit because if you burn out
that whole network has to get rebooted
um
as an example i can't believe how
constant this is with what i want to
talk about
so sweet all right
i would i would believe in in
synchronicity i made a few notes uh but
uh i i don't know if i need to consult
them very much okay so
let's a slight bit of context as i
mentioned i just finished
the play by albert camus um
excellent book i mean and of course in
many many many ways
uh resonantly uh relevant to what's
going on
right now um in a profound way um i'm
reading it
with my friend dan chappie he's the guy
i've done all the work on on the with
the rovers on mars
and all the technology around that um
and we're both camus fans
and he told me there's a character in
the book i don't know if you're familiar
with the book but there's a character in
what you are
okay so he told me throughout um that i
was terror
um and that's uh that's he is so he made
that uh
identification and he was very confident
about it um and then as i
as i went along i'm more and more
acquiesced and i thought yes
uh this is uh and of course uh i won't
say other bookends around
but towards the end of the book um
teru says something now i knew this
quote had come from camus but the
association with peru was particularly
it really sunk into my heart because of
the identification
hero says you know how to be a saint
without god
is the problem i'm up against today
okay so let me let me try and and how
does how
how so and then i realized okay that's
that's that's a really pertinent way and
the fact that he's saying that within
the context
of a plague of course made it deeply
resonant for me
all right and so then i started thinking
about this and i started thinking about
well as i've been trying to wrestle with
that question i take it very seriously
it's in some ways a very accurate
self-description as well
and so and notice already you've already
been talking about virtue
and that sort of brings this up right
away and then i thought about these four
figures
that i've been talking about because the
say the saint actually belongs to
you know a family there's the shaman
there's the sage there's the saint and
i'm trying to work out what the saint is
by putting him
him or her into that family and then you
know find the genus
do the aristotle thing find the genus
and then work out the specific
differences but then i said but there's
a fourth one that doesn't properly
belong but is often mistakenly put in
this category
and that's the star that's the star
now how does this connect with what
you're just right man when people become
stars
right celebrities right and then i'm
thinking
how does this resonate with what you're
saying because the shaman
right and the sage and the saint
are all figures that transcend
the normal humanity but do not grasp at
godhood
they do exactly what you're talking
about they find the place
to like be as much as they can
but they never give in to at least when
they're
behaving as they should as right think
about the sage
that goes too far in their
identification with god
because blasphemous the sage that
the saint the sage that thinks they have
god-like wisdom has brought forgotten
socrates
completely and utterly the shaman
who can't return from the sole flight is
no help
uh to his community right there's no
help with community
but the star doesn't fall into that
the star is expected to just rise and
rise and rise
and they're not allowed to fall at all
in fact if the star stall
starts to fall at all they're
immediately attacked
and cancelled and vilified
right and i thought what's going on so
first of all
what does it mean to be a saint as
opposed to just a shaman
or a sage and i'd like to talk to you
with that but then
what is it about the sa the saint
the shaman and the sage that
is reliably different from
the star and so
one way to think about the at least the
myth of jordan peterson whether or not
this is an
accurate description of this biography
that's a much more complex and difficult
question i think there's accuracy to it
but i would not claim
that it is completely uh that it is
complete or coherent
but let's say the myth is of somebody
and
listen to the language of a meteoric
rise right
to stardom he was he's been described as
a star
and a rock star right but
when he tried but i think initially
jordan wanted to be the shamanic healer
or he wanted to be the sage advisor
or he wanted to be the saintly
exemplification of virtue
but he didn't stay in those
he got sucked into stardom and stardom
is a place that blows that apart because
it mistakes right it mistakes
optimization with right with
as as maximization of some function
so what's interesting to me are these
people who
serve as vectors by which the network
can bootstrap it in the way you said we
need to give to
generation z the shamans bootstrapped
cognition the upper paleolithic
transition
the sages bootstrapped the axial
revolution
the saints bootstrapped the christian
but they did it without doing the thing
you worried about
but that you're worrying about here do
you see what i do they don't they don't
i mean obviously they're individuals who
fail i'm talking about the when the type
when this archetype is working when
these architects are working
i'm trying to get out what's going on in
those individuals both what is
genetically shared
and what is specifically different
between them because
i propose to you that we need something
beyond the shaman
the sage and the saint but not the star
so do you see how this is actually
really resonant with what you're talking
about
yeah well yes and what i'm noticing is
like
would you say if you were using you
you'd call it synchronicity
i'm feeling i don't know if there's a
word for it
ah okay just hold on
so one of the things that why is this
happening so
one of the words i would use to describe
the thing that is called synchronicity
is a little bit like when you get your
lenses into focus
yeah yeah it's that it's that it's that
feeling of insight when a whole bunch of
different
experiences in the outside all of which
have their own complexity
certain elements of those distinct
experiences uh remind you
of the thing that ultimately was the
shift in you you're like oh
the shift in you has integrated
wholeness and then you project back out
to those and integrated wholeness that
was happening in the outside
but part of that actually is that that
lensing shift and i feel
in my the back of my mind something that
wants to go there like there's an
effort to try to bring something into
clarity uh but the lens is not a camera
lens it's like
you know thousands of lenses that
actually have to get into arrangement so
that they have the right
uh i guess they're coming
in a resonance so
i'm also holding that really interesting
metaphor like this the circuit like the
physical groundedness of the circuit
and that notion of the of ground right
that notion of the
the the energy like literally energy not
metaphorically energy literally
electrical energy that flows into
something when it's not grounded
uh it's short circuits right that's the
fall
of the star right the collapse of the
star is is that and so there's something
like an
ungroundedness yep that is part of that
move and so it'd be an interesting
question to say
okay hold on that's cool um so what i
had proposed
was like the the next buddha is a sangha
that it's it's the thing that we're
challenged with right now
is to understand how not to do this
thing in the form of individuals
maybe that's exactly what the star is
the star is an effort to do as an
individual which properly belongs in a
network
that's right because you can't no given
individual human can possibly hold the
energy and complexity that is actually
looking to flow through that point
but because the energy and complexity
does want to float to that point
if you embody it meaningfully i.e if you
can embody
shaman sage and saint meaningfully and
begin to
and to begin to integrate them that
energy will flow into you which will
then begin to raise you up but by
raising it up it actually pulls you away
from the graph
so you actually get a reciprocal uh
collapse meaning that
precisely the degree to it you have the
capacity to actually hold that energy
you're setting yourself up for real
problems because if you pull away from
your actual communitas from your actual
network graph
you will lose this the grounding that
you need to have to
avoid a collapse so there's an asymmetry
problem there which is to say
the star becomes superhuman becomes more
than human becomes too godlike and
therefore
loses connection with the groundedness
of
humanity the groundedness of literally
the actual relationships of other people
that hold the capacity and support them
so the energy can flow through them
so there's like a humiliation effect
that is necessary to maintain the
capacity of the individual to stay
grounded and enmeshed but also a
recognition of the of the fact that the
next buddha is the sengha like
no one individual that moves too far if
the relationships break
if the relationships can't hold what's
happening you've missed it so you have
to go back down and say okay
we can only move if we progress in a
fashion where we're coming together
okay this one last piece i remember
having this insight
many years ago maybe a decade ago um
maybe even 15 years ago and it was
something like you know why are you
doing what you're doing
and i said well the primary reason why
i'll say the first part
first part um i have certainly for a
very long time
been quite a misanthrope and so i don't
really have a very high degree of
personal interpersonal like yay
in interacting with other people or with
people in general although
examples of what people have done are
amazing but
broadly speaking and certainly 15 years
ago not a big fan of people
um and so a question is like well why
are you doing what you're doing and the
answer is in fact
i i thought through the problem and i
reached the conclusion
that the only way that we can actually
solve this thing
is that we have to solve it in a fashion
which encompasses effectively everybody
yeah there is no way to save me there's
no way to save my family there's no way
to save my tribe there's no way to save
my nation
there's no way to save that subset of
the total humanity that i care about the
most
without in fact also effectively saving
everybody
there's an up and there's a down and the
up is big and the down is big
well this is what i'm saying here is
that same thing right the the
the magnitude of the energy and
information that needs to flow
through the system and the system here
is humans in relationship with each
other and probably technology
is enormous right it's just
incomprehensible how big it is
and no given individual or subset of the
of the whole
could possibly hold it and so the
challenge is to say okay how do we
progressively allow
that generative capacity to flow in
through the individuals who are
sensitive to it
don't blow your circuit right use that
to build more capacity in the network
that is around you
that now becomes effectively a node in
some sense right that can't blow its
circuit it becomes a
kind of a fractal network graph but is
able to flow that energy to increase its
own interior
capacity at each individual node in its
relationships right basically you're
adding
stronger gauge wire and better circuit
breaker
and then and then builds the its
connectivity to the exterior right it
has to be a generative process where
hey person over there who i don't know i
have right now an intrinsic
interest in your betterment in your
well-being and you're being made
more what you are capable of of being
like for you to achieve your highest
in yourself and for who you are because
at the end of the day
my network needs you and it's a very
simple like very simple equation at the
end of the day
and there's the only question is really
a matter of like right relationship and
right timing
yeah i can't i currently don't have the
capacity to support you beyond this
level now
for whatever reason and your needs are x
y and z so we just need to sort of
constantly find
what is our right relationship in this
moment and how does it up gradient
so that we're continually increasing the
quality of our individual collectives
and capacity to support each other
in that reciprocal opening
wow jordan that was both eloquent
and revealing of you as a person so
that that's a uh sorry i mean this
seriously
that's that's a noble transformation
that i've gone through
right to go on from being misanthropic
uh
uh to uh something that to my mind is
filetic or perhaps even agape
in its orientation mm-hmm yeah
so you can say i love my kids quite
dearly yeah
yeah yeah yeah and it got
the the experience i mean this is the
christian metaphor the experience
of the gothic love of your children is
supposed to be a metaphor that you exact
outwards
uh towards all people yeah right
the fact that that happened for you is
uh
makes a lot of sense okay so that's
great um but i'm still up against
tehru's problem that like he says the
problem i'm up against because
i was thinking you know the shaman and
in different ways
the shaman and the sage and the saints
but especially the saint peru's um what
to aspire to right they do
epitomize that virtue you're talking
about the virtue there's two virtues
here
there's the virtue of humility and then
the related virtue
of something like you know um philia or
charitas
the the sense of you know belonging to
the ecclesia
if you're a saint uh belonging to the
school if you're a sage
and of course belonging to the tribe if
you're a shaman and those two things are
paired together
right but teru's problem is
the thing that did that that kept people
that put a ceiling on icarus
and kept people bound together was
the divine god that's why he's in the
problem he's in
how do you it's right how are you to be
a saint
without a god i mean one of the ways of
thinking why we have stars is because we
have the death of god
we fling people into the heavens because
we find the heavens empty
but they can't stay there like icarus
they fall back
down right right right right and so
yeah yeah it's a bi-variable problem
so so i'm seeing like two images one
image is the story that you're telling
right now which is precisely
the notion of and it's funny it's like
the helpful
you know the helpful uh wrathful god
when he sees daedalus going too high
like whacks him on the head and says
stay
there um which is i don't know
treat the metaphor you know this is the
the the
kind of a bad father parenting style
right instead of inculcating in daedalus
the wisdom to make effective choices
creates an extrinsic uh kind of
enforcement regime
that ensures that daedalus stays within
effective operating parameters
but without becoming responsible himself
right so that's the that's the problem
of god
all right so you've got a you know bad
god gets good results through bad
methods that effectively make people
weak
um okay that's that's one side of this
equation the other side of the equation
is i'm seeing um what is it called like
all right let's go with like a
like like an evangelical it's actually
almost like a black church where it's
like
you know giving it up to jesus like how
do you maintain the capacity
to stay grounded to stay
wholesome in a world that is tragic
and unjust right because the key insight
here is not
how do i say it right all right we do
the same thing bad guy good god so
um the key inside is look more or less
all of us
and some of us all the time but not all
of us all the time are faced with
that problem and faced with more than we
could possibly hope to bear
now if we if we can't offload that
if we don't have a place to put that
where we have faith
that it's going to be taken care of
right if we if we try to take
responsibility for it then we'll just be
crushed
and that's not gonna work right so it
can be very practical and there's a
psychological move here that's crucial
at a psychological level you have to
have some way
of offloading that which you perceive as
being important and needful
and necessary to address at some point
by somewhere by somebody
but is more than what you can handle
individually and psychologically if you
can't get that
move then you'll just be questioned and
this is like you know a simple example
is the notion of uh
being overwhelmed by a task i think i
think about a task
like just practically i think about the
task of what it's going to take for me
to rewire my rv to build my solar system
oh my god it's way too much now i'm
overwhelmed and one
classical psychological approaches say
okay well just focus on the bite that's
in front of you
right is there a piece that you can take
that's not overwhelming and get you
moving forward
yes okay now you can be practically
effective don't don't try to take the
whole mountain at once just take the
step ahead of you right so that
psychological move of being able to
offload something that's as much
that is again perceived as needful it
has to
be taken care of somebody somewhere
sometime has to take care of this
because
it's a real issue but i personally can't
take care of it right now
and the way to offload that in faith
which is to say to trust that it will be
that i'm not that i'm not how do i say
this
just uh stepping away from
responsibility right that i'm not being
irresponsible but rather this is a
higher responsibility i know that i can
hand
i can only take what i can't handle and
i'm trying to take that fully right
that's a move
so
now that so for the the bad god version
of that is precisely the move that i
actually become irresponsible
where i actually just push off into the
into the into the ether
into sort of an unconstrained hope of
things and then
and then basically and enter into
spiritual bypass like i'm not going to
take my own responsibility
that's right i'm going to use this
mechanism to exit that right that's
right so
we could say in some sense like it's
interesting i think there's a way to do
this but
the saints problem is is that
we no longer have access to bad god
which means that we have access we no
longer have access to the mechanisms
that
work the effective mechanisms that work
in the context of that framing of
divinity
that leaves us in trouble and we have
not yet found a way
to get what i'm characterizing as good
god which is this
this approach that that doesn't put us
in context where we are
either only able to achieve
effective operating parameters by virtue
of an extrinsic authority
structure within everything else and
also
where we don't have a tendency to defer
our personal responsibility into blind
faith or into
uh spiritual bypass right so that
complex
the complex of how do we maintain
effective operating parameters from
something that comes from our
interior something that comes from a
an ethos as opposed to a morality to use
the way that i describe those two
differences
which also very very practically
allows us to have this quality of trust
or faith
which is really just a practical
awareness of i gotta take what i can
take and can't take any more
um and with any luck other people will
tend to carry the other stuff right and
so it's a practical call right a call to
say
hey how do we do this and i like the
practicality of it you know i don't know
if you've ever
carried a heavy tree yeah lifted a log
and carried it on your shoulders
yeah i think there's that that sense of
like let's say there's like three or
four of us let's make it four
four of us we're kind of lifting the
tree and there's a fifth person and they
look at it and they see like ah
yeah that's too heavy for them you can
kind of see like the strain is too high
and they feel a calling of okay hey let
me help you out that sense of like help
and awareness
that's the that's the very it's very
simple like very practical
and we're gonna we're gonna lift this
tree and we're gonna test and see
and then there's a hope that the right
resources will arrive
to lift it if you've got a good team
that hope is is
is based in experience right so it's a
it's a it's a good term for that it's
like a hmm
anyway it's it's a good hope like it's a
it's a it's a very reasonable hope it's
like the hope that the uh
you know when you're watching a
basketball team when suddenly one of the
players just starts sprinting down the
court
and when they jump in the air the ball
magically lands in their hands for a uh
for
all of you like that's it right you just
kind of hope that the signal that you
just got that tells you that the thing
is going to happen the way it's going to
happen without you necessarily having
certainty that the the thing over here
is going to do what it's going to do and
yet it does
like becoming a skillful network like
that allows us to have
practical hope that we can only focus on
what is ours to focus on
and expect that the network itself will
begin to hold more and more of it
so there's a closure on that previous
topology that i was describing which is
that so i think that maybe that's the
move right we to say okay i'm going to
make a distinction between
and bad god i don't mean evil god i just
mean like a an older version method of
this set of techniques that had
effectiveness within certain constraints
but has a whole bunch of failure
conditions not the least which is
reciprocal closing as an end point
right right and this new thing which is
just the higher version that frees it
from its bat from its sort of more
uh iron age we're all going to die
anyway we kind of just need to make it
to the next
you know generation point and said no no
we really need to get this really clean
and actually be
a much clearer version say of the divine
that was really good that was very
helpful so
let me try and
pick up on some points that resonate i
like for example the parental metaphor
uh so you good parenting is generally
between permissive and punitive um
you know so the idea is um you use the
minimal
amount of force to bring about the
compliance that is
beyond the child on its own but that the
child is capable of managing with your
help
the zone of proximal development so
timmy doesn't want to do x
um you know punish timmy just and punish
that punitive
you know just allow timmy to do whatever
timmy wants
right um sorry this is not meant to be
condescending i'm just using your
parental
analogy but what you do is you you you
try and you have to finesse the minimal
amount of force to get
timmy to try something that doesn't make
sense to me right now
but with you present co-present with
timmy it will make sense to timmy once
timmy has taken the developmental leap
right and so that's sort of that that's
sort of parenting
parental links like so it that's why
cultivation metaphors are used right
you know you know if you try to make the
plant grow you'll kill it if you just
let the leave the plant alone it dies or
it grows
it goes wild right you you the
cultivation
and there's deep connections between
cultivation cultists and culture
and so that's they're resonating so i'm
thinking about that
and i think that's really good but i i
want to
i want to i want to sort of try and
analogize that
and and try to explicate and draw out
your analogy
uh even more uh so let's call what's
let's let's um i forget i think the name
is authoritative
that which falls between uh permissive
and punitive and that brings up just
exactly the point i want to make right
so we had this idea
that well look at the word authority
and what what what makes people trust
and what people what makes people not go
too far but also not avoid
responsibility is a sense of
authority now i agree with you that
we've got to get an authority that is
between
permissiveness and punitive
and then the problem that
has been sort of parentally pointed to
um i'll use the biblical notion but
there are i think analogous notions in
taoism
um in buddhism right is idolatry
that people give they give too much
authority to the wrong thing
right they get too much authority right
that's that that's the problem
and so i've been thinking about that and
of course we are struggling with that
and there's i think there's a
correlation between
giving somebody too much authority
and then becoming a star and the
idolatry and that i don't
burns them out okay yeah
yeah oh how cool is that okay so so
uh okay let's see so idolatry
and it has to do with the notion of
formal identity
yes and it happens is you give authority
and this is like we have this
classic kind of get a good bad yeah so
yeah
zach calls it has a concept he called
teacherly authority teaching the
authority has to do with the ordinary
up gradient of prestige that human
beings are oriented to
that that particular person over there
knows the what the [ __ ] they're about
yeah and they're honestly trying to
share it with quality i will pay
attention right that's the teacher the
authority
okay very much then you have this this
idolatrous move
which is the replacement of the real
human
with the with the formal identity that
is now
a teacher right so now instead of
teaching the authority being embedded in
the actual complex lived imminent
reality of the human being the real
relationship
you have the formal role of teacher and
the and the
the expectation that one should be in
relationship with some random dude
because he has the title teacher
attached to his identity is what we call
bad authority
right now he has assumed authority that
he is not in fact
even main vaguely earned right right so
now you've got your cool
the concept of the star and i think
that's exactly i think you're nailing it
there which is what happens with the
stars the star becomes
reified and now the formal identity so
jordan peterson is no longer
the actual living embodied fully
imminent
human being jordan peterson he is the
identity structure
right the identity structure is now
conferred
a very large amount of of uh both
good and bad attention yeah yeah
which gives that access so you want to
ride that
ride that power suit right you want to
ride that wave like oh my god now being
this new this identity gives me access
to capacity to do great good in the
world
yeah yeah yeah but it comes with a
terrible price
which is that it also will be attached
to all kinds of other things will be
attached to it but most important
terrible price is
it ain't you yeah it never was you right
it's actually a
formal it's it's that it's an idol it's
you you've become
you you yourself have become idolatrous
yes you become an idol
right yes therein lies the problem yes
yes so sacred cows get sacrificed yes
so uh now i want to make another move i
like
you see what i'm trying to do here i did
this with uh with andrew
um and i think chris i was trying to say
how do you bring in sort of a sequence
of proposals that are like
argumentation into the biological
process
and i'm trying to also exemplify
something here because i had
right so i schematized an argument but i
i'm leaving
sorry i hope this is this sounds
cooperative
i'm trying to leave space to afford so
that you can
bring something into it that's
unanticipated by my argument
so that my argument has to shift and
adapt yeah
i hope you feel that's happening so the
move i want to make now is to
and it is to pick up on the next buddha
is the sangha
okay so and and and and you're right the
problem with stars is the it
is the individualization of authority
that's part of the problematic
right it's not all of the problematic
but that's part of it
so i came back to this notion of
authority
and how it's grounded ultimately in the
narrative
metaphor of the author the author who
writes a story right that's where the
that's where we get
the notion of authority from and then i
was thinking
and i thought back to camu and i'm
thinking through the plague and the
point about the plague right is the
breakdown of narrative
right um human beings keep trying all
these narratives
on the plague and the plague keeps
basically giving them the finger
right and saying so try that narrative
if you want look what i can do
oh try that narrative you want look what
i can do and try to
and then you get you get the two figures
of ryu and taru
who slowly stopped a ban they abandoned
the narrative projection
they abandoned the narrative projection
and then it occurred to me
and again i'm thinking also of you know
your game be stopped about trying to
break the fundamental grammar in a deep
way
so i'm gonna i want to try very
carefully here and i'm saying this
cautiously
and i'm not fully committed to it
because the language isn't completely
adequate but it's the only language i
have right now
i think our notion of god
the mythological notion is a narrative
notion
right and what we're seeing right now
is not the breakdown of a narrative
we're seeing the breakdown of
narrativity
that's the death of god okay then i re
and then but i've been thinking about
this because i think about this in terms
of a debate i had with
not a debate a deal logos better because
it was wonderful with paul vander clay
and jonathan pajot but i was trying to
argue that we should
shift the sacred
from narrative to the logos
and here and and part of the proposal
went like this let's go back to the
parenting metaphor
okay children are not naturally narrow
narrative we have to do the narrative
practice hypothesis they're not
naturally metaphorical
we have to teach them this we have to
practice it but what
are they naturally what is it that they
naturally have
that affords us being able to teach them
narrative and metaphor
they are naturally dialogical that's all
of the work of tomasello and all the
work that's coming out
kids come ready like joint attention
they take turns they're memetic
right they so dear logos is more
primordial and more grounding and i
thought of your
argument about we need to drop to the
deepest
levels to access what is most
perennially powerful
right now so we have to drop below the
narrative level
we have to drop below the narrative
level of authority
that's and right and we have to drop
into seeing no no what it
ultimately is grounded in is dia logos
and dialogos
is not a finite story it's an infinite
game
right right no i mean i was literally i
was
i was about to drop your brother karst
right in the middle of it so you just
pulled it
out which is great so i don't have to we
don't have to talk anymore like we're
actually on so much synthetic just the
words will come from whatever mouth
happens to be open
great yes so much yes that's it like
narrative
is all about being right it's a finite
game
the trick is can i get the right
narrative can i get everybody else to
adopt my narrative
dialogos is intrinsically the inverse of
that or the converse maybe it's the
opening right it's a playful
relationship rather than the move is not
a move of me saying your narrative is
wrong
the move is to say okay how do i extend
this how do i build more how do i make
it's a generative grammar right it's
intrinsically a creative invitation to
continuing to play
more and more awesomely see narratives
build heroes
via logos builds networks yes
oh another great one yes absolutely
narratives build heroes narratives
create that formal context right you
become the
narrative is actually narrative is the
the idolatry narrative is the thing that
creates that movement away from being
who you are
in place to playing a role in a
narrative
that's right narratives really has that
notion of currency right narratives
create
ah yeah hold on let me rewind back here
[Music]
yes narrative we're in the process of
recognizing that any narrative that can
be produced by
this particular grammar is the problem
there is no narrative that solves the
problem the problem is the grammar
produces these things
these things are the problem the answer
is to
change the grammar and then to change
the
what de lloyd's would call the abstract
machine which is the playing out of the
grammar in context
that move is the same move that i
described in the game a game b
distinction but now we're finally
actually getting some real clothing on
it
yeah um so yeah that's what i'm trying
to do that's right
yes yes so teru's problem
is right is to being a saint without god
is to break the narrativity that binds
the saint
as the religious hero to god as the
ultimate authority of a story
yeah and that's what he has to break
both sides
right he has to break out of it and
that's what camus
is of course trying to do throughout in
his work right he's trying to
feel what's that like and and what what
are the virtues that will be disclosed
when we open
up the agent and the re arena in this
translative fashion because here's one
thing
that kamu is aware of and this came up
in my discussion with paul and
jonathan narrative is indispensable for
getting us to
adulthood there's no there's nothing
right deal logos comes first but if you
don't get narrative you don't become a
temporarily extended self
right you don't get capacities for
non-logical identity
what we're largely practicing right
dialogos gives us our first
taste of non-logical identity but
narrative
exacts it and extends it right onto
logically and temporally becomes
become we become temporally and modally
extended selves
through narrative but the point is right
like everything else
we can i we can that has fallen into a
an idolatry
we have to break out of that we have to
see something that is theological
but not pre-narrative but post-narrative
dialogic
post-narrative dialogic is what we what
i'm arguing is what we
we need if we're going to learn how to
be saint without god
because that's what that's what we need
right now
so i'm seeing two things let me do me
the second one
why why do i need to number them you
don't know who they are
um so i'm with my daughter at the beach
and my wife is talking to me about a
notion that she's come into contact with
in parenting
which i immediately she says i'm like
yeah for sure begin adopting that as a
a method and it has to do with the being
very conscious
of the language you're using being very
conscious of the degree to which
you're creating a a narrative
an obligate narrative primary mind
right and it works this way um
your daughter is sitting there in the
sand and she sees some object maybe it's
you know a
crab and you point at it and you say
that's a crab
and then you tell a story be careful
crabs can pinch
right which is useful right in fact i
think for almost all parents that
in particular contemporary environment
that's kind of parenting right your job
is to
to to weave together a sense-making
fabric
through narrative instruction that loads
on a construct in the mind
that can effectively pattern match from
sensorium to
uh identity and then has a whole bunch
of adjectives and affordances attached
to that identity so you've got good
behavior
that's all moral right that's all
morality in the sense that i was using
her it's all bad god and
the top down authoritative constraint
the the alternative
which is that what i'd say is the solve
to this problem is to be conscious of
of actually orienting in the direction
of wonder so
and just like the simple question i
wonder what i wonder what would happen
if
i wonder what might happen here i wonder
how that right to have as a primary mode
of interpersonal
pedagogy and invitation to wonder
and what's interesting is notice the
difference there's no third person
omniscient
that is right god pointing and telling
you
loading that is it's actually very first
person i wonder which is a really
interesting invitation because
she may not give a [ __ ] if she's two
years old she may be like i don't wonder
that i'm gonna go do this
right it's an invitation to do are you
also interested in this wondering
if so then we can wonder together and if
not you don't really feel
you know it's an invitation that doesn't
have constraint and that's
that's you know that's dialogue right
that's an invitation into
something where we begin to co-create a
um what you call a wonderful like a a
world of of intrigue and and playing
with the mystery
as opposed to trying to box it up with
pre-framed knowings of what it is
okay so two riffing responses to that
right away so ellen langer one of the
first people to bring mindfulness
uh into uh the western academic frame
you know she talks about soft vigilance
versus heart focus but she also talks
about uh conditional versus absolute
learning
so and what you what she did is she went
into textbooks
and textbooks are almost always at all
absolute learning so absolute learning
is
it is an x conditional learning is one
way of thinking about this
is as and that it is an axe right so the
framing around
the proposition that you want to pass on
is one of
radical identification versus
conditional identification
and what she found and this comes to no
surprise that if you give people
absolute learning they are not as good
at learning they're good they're very
good at
storing the proposition but they're not
good learners
using the proposition using the
knowledge they don't have the
understanding
right the grasping the significance but
which is supported by doing conditional
language so that's one piece
so conditional versus absolute the
second
right is uh dweck's notion of
fixed versus malleable mindset so
if i praise you and say you're bright
you will think of yourself as having a
fixed trait and then what you do is you
get into image management
because you don't want that trait to be
lost yep
but if i praise you for the process i i
say
wow that was a very good skill you just
use
or that was a great sequence you went
through i love that learning process if
so if you praise the process
then what happens is people will
actually improve their performance
and they will expose themselves to risk
because they're not
trying to manage a fixed rate they're
trying to
grow a malleable trade now what's what's
really interesting
about that by the way is getting people
to shift the focus from the product to
the process it's also central to making
them more rational
that's so people tend to over fixate on
the products of their cognition
and not enough on the process and that's
what makes them subject to
self-deception
so here's the thing what if you you know
if you had the
conditional representation of the arena
that's your wonder
hey i wonder what this is here's one way
of thinking about it
there's another way of thinking about it
and then also a malleable
agency hey what you just did there was a
really good process it's a really great
virtue
that's a really impressive skill right
yeah
yeah absolutely this is exactly right
and and i think that if i kind of i'm
going to pop it up and
if you don't mind i'd also like to bring
in something over here that is kind of
keeps showing up
and i think it might be really
interesting so let me pop this up so
there's this a big move that's happened
that's funny i thought about it i'll use
nietzsche right now
nietzsche makes the distinction between
the warrior and the soldier
yeah um manuel delanda points out the
whole history of the tailorization the
forwardization
move of people in general right through
code disciplinary power
which is to say that move what you're
describing right there
and the the the trade-off or or what
happens
if if if i optimize
for the what was the kind of learning
that was just
direct direct learning there's absolute
versus conditional
right and then there's fixed traits
versus malleable traits
so basically if i optimize for absolute
learning
in a in a particular strategic landscape
i can achieve local optima yes
all right i can beat you to that thing
and if
if i know what the thing is and i you
know i'm frederick the great
and i train all my soldiers to be this
clockwork army and everybody does
exactly this thing
i get this it turns out to be a
short-term advantage
yeah right over somebody who puts a
longer-term investment in
capacity right right this constant
trade-off between
a game that is iterating by a series of
short-term local optima
at the expense of games that are
focusing on on global optima
is like a fundamental conundrum right
it's a it's a game theoretic
dynamic that describes a lot of the big
problems yeah i think
at the core of relevance realization
that's why i put it into the relevance
realization machinery
exactly so the was it
was our previous conversation with greg
maybe it was but that that notion of
being able to say look there's a way to
have your cake and eat it too
there's a way to have the the moment
you're in
be kind of as good as it gets at the
local level
and also be directly connected in
continuity
to the best possible long-term strategy
and there's something about like when
the niche is changing
fast enough that local optima just keeps
falling they keep evaporating
but the only valid strategy is something
that's actually taking this bigger
approach this i think a big part of the
current moment why the pivot from
gaming to game b is is uh is both
relevant and salient right now
all right sort of let me do the second
move though okay
please all right so the second move is
uh maybe a little bit of like an
invitation for for i guess it's paul and
jonathan
so my my uncle who was only 16 years
older than me
um he passed away about i gotta think
like
two years ago not long ago maybe even a
year ago
yeah a year and a half ago um
and he was he was a deacon in the
catholic church
right so which is you know takes a
significant amount of dedication
and energy yeah and one of the things
that he and i did in the last
he had cancer so we sort of took a
period of time
in the last six months a year
is we read the bible together remotely
like i would read portions of it then we
would talk about it
and i was i was really reminded of the
conversation around
uh the book of acts and what we were
just talking
about and what i mean by that is and i
was just
as i was curious i wonder i wonder if
the movement
from the so the fulfillment of the book
right and the line
of of the crucifixion the resurrection
followed by the holy spirit right and
then
that and the the the continuity or the
continuation
of of the of the church is
the the holy spirit's presence in the
church which is to say in the people
themselves
right and it feels to me like that's a
very interesting relationship what we
were just talking about right the
movement from
a old testament god that lives
outside as a separate entity that
provides wrath
to enforce obligate behavior
and this transition to the holy spirit
which is actually
imminent in the people in the whole of
the church who are now fully responsible
for interrelating with each other and
becoming capable as individuals
of feeling and living with the spirit
but then also living through it
right living living it into the world um
as the good
right the thing that i was describing as
the good god and it contains i think
everything we're describing like all the
words that we're using and all the
transitions
all uh talk about what that is like on
that other side
so that came to me as well well i think
that's relevant i mean
chris and i talk about the third factor
that emerges in the dialectic
practice like when dialogue when
dialectic of before it's the emergence
of the logos
we talk about the third factor as the
geist uh because we wanted to determine
this
the german term because it stands
between mind and spirit right
yeah intelligence and consciousness um
and so that's something that we're sort
of working out in the whole
the cognitive science of dialectic india
logos so let's keep that as
one of the balls i'm going to try and
juggle here but i'm thinking of a couple
of things
about the holy spirit first of all you
know it's
it's it's the logos becoming dear logos
jesus is the logos but what does he say
where two or three are gathered in my
name there i am also
and there's a connection there between
the holy spirit right coming into the
logos
and then you get the recommendation to
not try to plan what you're going to say
when you come before the emperor the
powers of the principalities
don't rehearse a narrative or a story
because you will be clamping down
on the possibility of the spirit
speaking to you
the third right is the idea that when
we're praying
the holy spirit is actually from the
deepest level
praying through us and affording our
prayer
and so there is i know this is heretical
but
maybe this is the time of all heresies
um right uh
there's a way of reinterpreting the holy
spirit especially as it's portrayed
functionally i guess of the way i'm
trying to use it and phenomenologically
uh in in the new testament especially
the book of acts
it's consonant with it being you know a
dialogical entity
that is trying to be you know
post-narrative or trans-narrative
in some really important
fashion so i think that's deeply deeply
right
funny i mean i guess i'm listening with
particular ears but i didn't hear
anything heretical on what you just said
and you were using a certain set of
words but i if i understand what you
mean by
you know jesus was the logos yeah but
then the
the the commandment the requirements to
move to dear logos right and that must
be
uh two or three right gatherings in the
coming
um
i i don't know for some reason that felt
like that was a way of saying it that if
i listened clearly
the spirit was speaking perhaps
yes um and maybe i'm wrong i'm sure that
we will have
comments that will let us give us more
information on that
um but that feels right and let me just
kind of put another piece in there
one of the a conversation i had with
someone um was about
how do i say it like
concern about separation from their
lived experience in the church
catholic church in this case um and as i
listened
what i diagnosed was precisely the
replacement of narrative
for the logos the replacement of
narrative for the actual spirit
yeah and this is a super common place
right to pray
my wife right she was raised catholic it
kind of blew her mind
when she said well what kind of what
narrative are you engaging in when
you're praying
i was like none like that seems like
that would totally get in the way
yes yeah yeah um and then she's like
wait oh wow so
this the idea of like hey guys this is a
set of words that
that you kind of if you repeat it
practically speaking maybe right
practically speaking it's like a mantra
practically speaking
it will help you get into the place that
we will call prayer
right over here but then the mistake of
oh no this is prayer in and of itself
even if you don't
get to the place and then this is in
fact so much prayer that you don't never
you can't even get to the place you
forget it exists right so that kind of
that movement
um i would say that's heresy
and i would say even if it comes from a
really nice medieval sensibility
right which is hey you know it's really
hard this is
hard living is hard we got barbarians
all the time plagues all the time like
it's a mess
and so we kind of got to get some psycho
technologies in place that have
like their you know water wheels and
cranks that successfully you know grind
the wheat so we're going to do this
we're going to put these techniques in
place that
have some degree of efficacy but then of
course right the idolatry of the
technique is just as bad as the idolatry
of the person
yeah um
yeah i guess that's all i thought that
was a the one
the water flowed through and now i'm
done empty no i like i like that
that disjunct um
and i think i can circle back to the
point you made about people remaining
grounded and not losing their humanity
this came up in the discussion with uh
paul and jonathan
wonderful discussion i highly recommend
it a real deal logos very powerful
um but i was pointing out jesus use of
parable and the work of sally mcfagg
who work on metaphorical theology and a
book speaking in parables
and also related work i forget by whom
on
um the parabolic stories of uh that the
sufis used
and what mcflag points out is that
parables look like narratives but
they're not
right so i was using the one that's
always meant a great deal to me and i
remember reading uh carol shields
updated version
of the parable of the prodigal son and
the point is
this looks like a story and you're and
you're reading through it and here's all
the
archetypal roles on one son another the
servant the father
oh right and and you can see people
wanting to allegorize it well there's
god the father and all
but it doesn't work and the whole point
of the parable is exactly that
the whole point of the parable is if you
try to resolve it
if you try and say no no justice always
trumps compassion
no no compassion always trumps justice
you lose it our humanity is in the tonos
that cannot be captured by a narrative
it can only be captured dialogically
right it can only be captured
dialectically and the point about a
parable it's a it's a
it's what i call it a narrative time
bomb it looks like a narrative
you take it in and assimilate it as a
narrative and then it blows the holes
out of your narrative and opens you up
to a trans narrative accommodation
and so i think right if the holy spirit
is the spirit of the logos wow i don't
know i can't believe i'm doing this
and the logos is the the logos
most properly taught in that parenting
style that we're talking about
the wonderful parenting style by using
parable then i think we could actually
say
this is consonant with you know
chris you know and uh i don't know what
to call it
but you know i think it's a heretical
interpretation of christianity
that may actually again answer peru's
problem
of how to be a saint without god
yeah it does i think
so so the this this way of
right this way of because
you know and i think i i think of
the other great existentialists you
mentioned nietzsche but you think of
kirkegaard see me nietzsche does
something where he undermines narrative
by being multi-vocal
you don't know what nietzsche is
actually saying or what the story is
because he's uh he gives you he writes
like the bible there are many
conflicting stories and
perspectives and they all continually
undermine each other and so he's trying
to
he destabilizes anything right and and
that's powerful
um and and a lot of people don't get
that when they read nietzsche
they pay too much attention to the
content of what nietzsche says
and not enough to the manner of the
process they idolize nietzsche
rather than emulating him which is a big
mistake but i'm thinking of the other
one kirkegaard
right and kirkegaard writes in parables
he even
writes things that are called like that
are explicitly parables his novel many
of his novels have parabolic
parabolic structure to them in which he
like the diary of the seducer he gives
you this narrative
but then he undermines it from within
right because he's constantly
and although i have deep problems with
this
part of his thinking what i've been
thinking about recently and what i'm
sharing with you is
right and i don't like even his
terminology but i think this is what he
was trying to get at with the
tibialogical suspension of the ethical
and i'm going to use ethical the way you
use morality
okay so the point of the ideological is
meaning
ethics is bound into narrative
personhood
and there is something that is supposed
to be beyond that
that is trans personal and trans
narrative which human beings
are ultimately called to this is why you
get
the thing that within the within the
narrative
is horrific and it's in it and notice
what it's doing
it's a request from god to sacrifice a
person
right and narratives are all about
persons and their their evaluation
and that all that story always bothered
me and it bothered kirkegaard and
there's ways of interpreting that story
that i think are evil and pernicious
but i'm playing with the idea well maybe
that story
that story is exactly right what we're
talking about here is this a story of
well
ultimately narrative personhood
and the ethic right isn't ultimate
that it actually right the dialogical
relationship
to that which transcends the narrative
is
what is ultimate yeah right and there's
a parabolic structure in there
there's a story that actually undermines
all stories
so let's pivot to a conversation you and
i had
i think two times ago right which uses
another
language of paradigm yes right and we
talked about the notion of the context
of
acceleration
accelerating change the change in the
underlying reality of the context that
you're in
and then mismatch the paradigms breaking
apart faster because the
a paradigm is a narrative right yeah and
like
okay i get it so if i have a you know
things more or less don't change a lot
for 500 years
right we write a narrative we kind of
dial it in it's a solid narrative
and we run it and we kind of lose track
of it you know 200
300 years later we sort of lost track of
the fact that somebody at some point
created a narrative but when things are
changing rapidly enough that you
actually are seeing narratives emerge
break down emerge and break down in like
you know
months it becomes rather obvious
that that tool right that that grammar
right the narrative grammar the grammar
that produces paradigms
is no longer an effective way of being
an adaptive relationship with the real
reality that you happen to find yourself
in
i hadn't seen that oh my gosh
the connection between being trans
narrative and being
you know transparent digmatic i hadn't
oh my gosh thank you
that's that yes
exactly exactly
huh i had yes
yes very much oh that's beautiful jordan
that's beautiful what
so what what that means then is
right we're looking for i mean
and and you know when she was trying to
get this with beyond good and evil but
trying to get
you know post-paradigmatic post
moral i'll use your distinction and
post narrative in some court and
kind of right post um
authoritarian post authority right i'm
trying to think of the parenting styles
i'm trying to bring them all together
and we're trying to get that
and that's the way in which the next
buddha can be
the same and that's the way and there's
a way of being within that that's a
sainthood without
god yep which is to say that it's the
move from the logos to the deal logos
yes yes and what's funny about is that
in many ways it's i find it also to be
quite simple like
you talked about like what does the kid
come with like straight up
yeah yeah you know logos machinery is
what we've got
um and then we build other stuff on top
of it and
it is a what do they call it there's a
archaic revival there's like a little
bit of an archaic revival it's like okay
let's go to the deep stuff let's find
the deep deep deep stuff that's you know
billions of years or hundreds of
millions of years of adaptive capacity
and bring that back up but you know
we're not we're not going back
we're bringing it back up and then we're
resurfacing it in a whole new context
particularly
with an enormous amount of what i would
call consciousness meaning yes
a way of being aware of what we're
talking about now and actually having a
process a capacity to
improve the process right to name the
process as being good and then to
improve the process
along the vector of its goodness yeah
i would call that both consciousness and
rationality
in the way in which i've tried to expand
the notion of rationality
um so that to me
right i mean uh i haven't read a lot of
wilbur's work but he makes
he he he notes that um and maybe this is
relevant to jordan
peterson in some fashion wilbur says
that one of the problems with young is
what he calls the pre-trans fallacy
the young does not adequately
distinguish between pre-egoic
and trans-egoic that they can be deeply
confused together
and that can really mess people up so in
an analogous fashion
i want to distinguish between the
pre-narrative and the trans-narrative
versions of
the logos and that what we're trying to
do with conscious rationality
is not regress to pre-narrative dialogic
but to try and progress to
trans-narrative dialogic theologians
yes absolutely and just to be careful
also
since we've got cool greek prefixes
let's distinguish between
trans-narrative and meta-narrative yes
yes
right meta-narrative is just a bigger
narrative yes yes
trans-narrative is a different kind of
thing altogether exactly that's very
well said too
right that's very well said that's
excellent
well i think that was most of what i
wanted to
talk about did did i give you also a
place for you to
uh develop some of what you brought some
of your energy that you brought into
uh yeah yeah absolutely um in
a very sort of uh very secret way
i think it's exactly right there was a
moment
i just want to call this out as a gem um
that meant a lot to me i mean there was
a lot that was meaningful
and provocative and insightful but when
you said that what we were doing was
sort of putting clothes
on to some of your ideas or putting
flesh out of it i can't remember this
that really touched me very deeply oh
yeah
hmm gives me hope man excuse me hope
okay so i i i propose that we end it
here
yeah sounds good it's a good play but
but uh
this is not an ending in the narrative
sense uh it's like sart said
uh you never complete anything you only
abandon them
[Laughter]
that's awesome all right see you later
man
okay take good care let me know if you
want me to uh share this with you oh
please do yeah please do
okay well dude take care my friend bye